Inventory of the Miguel Aroche Parra papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Miguel Aroche Parra papers
1901-2011
2014C20
Hoover Institution Archives
53 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (24.2 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, internal bulletins, and printed matter, relating to political conditions in Mexico, and especially to political parties and electoral alliances of the left, including the Partido Comunista Mexicano, the Partido Obrero Campesino Mexicano, the Movimiento de Acción y Unidad Socialista, and the Partido de la Revolución Democrática.
Aroche Parra, Miguel, 1915-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Miguel Aroche Parra was a Mexican railroad unionist, Communist Party leader, a poet, author, and journalist and a columnist for Excelsior.
Aroche Parra, born in 1915, was an active member of the Partido Comunista Mexicano until 1950, when he helped found the Partido Obrero Campesino Mexicano, which became part of the Partido Popular Socialista in 1963. Aroche Parra, who played a leading role in the famous 1959 railroad strike, was imprisoned for more than seven years for taking part in that movement. In prison Aroche Parra began writing poems that were eventually compiled and published under the title 28 Poems of Love and Life.
An orthodox Marxist-Leninist, Aroche Parra criticized the Partido Revolucionario Institucional’s (PRI’s) long rule in Mexico. He wrote often about the labor movement in his country and criticized what he saw as the political repression of dissent by the Mexican government, especially the student movement of 1968. On international issues, Aroche Parra was a dedicated "anti-imperialist" who opposed what he saw as the malign influence of US power in Latin America and elsewhere in the world. In contrast, he wrote favorably about North Vietnam and North Korea.
Scope and Contents note
The Aroche Parra papers are made up mostly of correspondence, serial issues, and his writings, including original drafts of essays, poems, and his many articles written both for the organs of the political parties he was associated with and for publications such as Excelsior and Política with a wide audience in Mexico. Aroche Parra's articles and columns thus offer a running commentary on Mexican and international politics during a period of more than half a century.
The papers also contain position papers and other internal documents relating to his participation in radical politics, including those pertaining to the issues that led to his expulsion from the Communist Party of Mexico. In his later years, Aroche Parra served as a deputy representing the Partido de la Revolucion (PDR) in the Chamber of Deputies of the Mexican Congress; his papers contain a number of documents relating to the PDR’s formation.
In addition, drafts of many of Aroche Parra's poems. Inspired by the work of Pablo Neruda, they are often political in nature, although some are of a more personal, romantic nature.
Movimiento de Acción y Unidad Socialista (Mexico).; Partido Comunista Mexicano.; Partido de la Revolución Democrática (Mexico).; Partido Obrero Campesino Mexicano..; Communism--Mexico.; Mexico--Politics and government.; Socialism--Mexico.
- Writings and correspondence while in prison, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence with Paul Duddy, 1968-193 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Partido de la Revolución Democrática documents and a copy of Fuego Nuevo.
- Correspondence and articles, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Manifestos and political writings about ferrocarrilero strikes, 1961-1967 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Copies of articles, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- MAUS documents and copies of articles, 1970-2000 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Documents on Ambrosio Figueroa, 1976, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  Includes speeches to Camara de Diputados.
- Documents on 1994 elections, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  Includes PRD and ADN document.
- Partido de la Revolución Democrática, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Documents and correspondence relating to Mexican Revolution in Guerrero, 1920s (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Correspondence and speeches, 1941, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  Includes PCM documents and copies of articles.
- PCM and POCM correspondence, 1941-1958 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Miscellaneous documents, 1970s (Box-folder 2: 1)
- PSUM documents and international politics, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- PRD Documents, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Poetry, 1990s (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Copies of articles and periodicals, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Documents on PRD, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Copies of articles in El Sol de Acapulco, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Copies of articles in Excelsio r, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Copies of articles in Excelsior and documents on PRD, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Copies of articles in Excelsior and other newspapers, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  Includes ADN documents.
- Documents on Germán List Arzubide, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Articles in Excelsior, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Writings on PRD, 1999 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Copies of articles, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Copies of articles, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Various political materials, 1982 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- Poetry, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- Political writings on national and international issues, 1965-1971, 1996 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  Includes correspondence and drafts of articles.
- Documents on National Committee for Human Rights, 1950-2000 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  Includes correspondence and documents on ADN.
- PRD Documents, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 11)
- Manuscript copy of Efemerides, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Copies of articles, 1977, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  Includes reflections on 1991 elections.
- Copy of “El Activista Regional,”, 2008 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- MAUS documents, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- PCM and POCM documents, 1945-1958 (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Copies of articles, 1965 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Copies of articles, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 7)
- PCM correspondence, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Documents on PRD, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Facsimile of El Tiempo, November 1942-April 1943, May-October 1945 (Box 5)
- Facsimile of El Tiempo, May-October 1944, November 1944-April 1945 (Box 6)
- Notes and documents on dirty war in Guerrero, 1975-2008 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  Includes PRD documents.
- Correspondence and articles, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- PCM and POCM documents, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Correspondence of POCM, 1955-1965 (Box-folder 7: 4)
- MAUS documents, 1976 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- Copies of articles, 1943-1953 (Box-folder 7: 6)
- PRD documents, 1996 (Box-folder 7: 7)
- POCM documents and correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- Writings on Coalition of the Left, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 7: 10)
- PRD documents, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 7: 11)
- Copies of articles, 1998-2004 (Box-folder 7: 12)
- POCM documents, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Documents on Sino-Soviet split; Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Copies of articles, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Copies of articles, 1985-1993 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- Correspondence and articles, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Articles and PRD documents, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 8: 6)
- MAUS documents, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 7)
- Poetry on Vietnam, 1972-1985 (Box-folder 8: 8)
- Poetry and articles, 1967-1984 (Box-folder 8: 9)
- “Canto a Guerrero”, undated (Box-folder 8: 10)
- Correspondence and articles, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 8: 11)
- Articles published in Excelsior, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8: 12)
- Poetry and cultural writings, 1983 (Box-folder 8: 13)
- MAUS documents and manuscript of “El Tio Jeculi,”, 1971, undated (Box-folder 8: 14)
- PRD documents, 1993 (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Copies of articles, 1983, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  Includes ADN and PRD documents.
- POCM documents, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 9: 3)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 9: 4)
- PRD documents, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 9: 5)
- Empty (Box-folder 9: 6)
- List of books to purchase, undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
- Misc. political papers, 1977 (Box-folder 9: 8)
- Correspondence, 1955, 1987 (Box-folder 9: 9)
- MAUS documents, 1973-1976, 1980, 1988 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  Includes correspondence and articles.
- Miscellaneous, 1982-1998 (Box-folder 9: 11)
- ADESE documents, 1994 (Box-folder 9: 12)
- Copies of articles, 1994 (Box-folder 9: 13)
- Copies of articles, “El Socialismo y el Hombres” by Che Guevara, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Documents on indigenous movement and rural development, 1980 (Box-folder 10: 2)
- Documents on Raul Isidro Burgos, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Documents on Caciquismo in Guerrero, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
- Copies of articles, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 10: 5)
- Copies of articles and corridos, undated (Box-folder 10: 6)
- “El Chivo,”, 1983 (Box-folder 10: 7)
- Poetry, undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
- ADESE documents and articles, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 10: 9)
- Articles published in Excelsior, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 10: 10)
- Newspaper clippings, 1983 (Box-folder 10: 11)
- Ferrocarrilero documents and correspondence, 1956-1984 (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Articles and speeches, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Writings on teachers and electric industry in Mexico, 1930s (Box-folder 11: 3)
- ADESE and ADN files, 1997 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Miscellaneous documents and speeches, 1957-2000 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  Includes PRD documents and correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 6)
- Speeches, articles, and MAUS correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 11: 7)
- Documents on ferrocarrilero arrests, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  Includes example of handwriting and hunger strike materials.
- Ephemera, 1984, 1984, 1990 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  Includes articles.
- “El Corrido Guerrerence,”, 2001 (Box-folder 11: 10)
- Documents on Libreria Nacional, 1988 (Box-folder 11: 11)
- Copies of speech on Cárdenas, 2001 (Box-folder 11: 12)
- PCM materials, 1939 (Box-folder 11: 13)
- “Juego Politico y Guerrilla Rural en Mexico” thesis by Raul Fernandez Gomez, 1980 (Box-folder 11: 14)
- Miscellaneous articles, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- MAUS and PST documents, 1974, 1986 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- PCM and POCM documents, 1951 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Congreso de Unidad Marxista, 1950-1958 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  Includes POCM documents.
- Miscellaneous documents on oil, 2005 (Box-folder 12: 5)
- Miscellaneous documents, 1991-2005 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- PRD documents, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Documents on Vietnam and dirty war in Guerrero, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 12: 8)
- ADN documents, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 12: 9)
- Articles and correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 12: 10)
- PRD documents and correspondence, 1954-1996 (Box-folder 12: 11)
  Includes various ephemera.
- Articles on PRD, 1981-1982, 1991 (Box-folder 12: 12)
  Includes correspondence.
- PRD materials, 1980, 1991 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  Includes newspaper clippings.
- Various publications, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 12: 14)
- Magazines and ephemera, 1976-2008 (Box-folder 13: 1)
- PRD documents, 2000 (Box-folder 13: 2)
- Writings on Germán List Arzubide, 1993 (Box-folder 13: 3)
- PRD documents, 1991 (Box-folder 13: 4)
- POCM documents and correspondence while in prison, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 13: 5)
- Copies of Voz Proletaria, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 13: 6)
- Copies of articles and speeches and ephemera, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 13: 7)
- Various, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 13: 8)
- POCM documents, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 13: 9)
- Articles and correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 14: 1)
- Documents on rural school Ayotzinapa, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 14: 2)
- Articles and correspondence, 1963-1975 (Box-folder 14: 3)
- PRD documents, 1992 (Box-folder 14: 4)
- PRD documents and articles, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 14: 5)
- Articles and correspondence, 1976-1991 (Box-folder 14: 6)
- Plan de Ayala, 1964, 1953, 1964 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  Includes “Luciano, Moro y el Utopismo de Vasco de Quiroga.”
- Document listing publications of Guerrero., 1992 (Box-folder 14: 8)
- PRD documents or relating to PRD, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 14: 9)
- Copies of articles published in El Sol de Acapulco, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 14: 10)
- Correspondence and ephemera, 1969-1971, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 14: 11)
- Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 14: 12)
- Writings on education and agriculture, undated (Box-folder 15: 1)
  Includes documents on labor disputes and other assorted issues and political writings, domestic and international.
- Writings on Ayotzinapa Rural Normal School and work as a teacher, 1970s (Box-folder 15: 2)
- Correspondence PP, POCM and PCM, 1950s (Box-folder 15: 3)
- Documents on the merging of PMS with PRD, undated (Box-folder 15: 4)
- PRD Documents, 1990s (Box-folder 15: 5)
- Documents on merging of POCM and PCM, 1959 (Box-folder 15: 6)
- Correspondence of MAUS and joining of PPS and POCM, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  Includes materials on Ferrocarilero strikes.
- Political papers on MAUS and PRD, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 15: 8)
- Political papers on MAUS, 1970s (Box-folder 15: 9)
- Writings on diverse topics, mostly foreign investment and economic crisis in Mexico, undated (Box-folder 15: 10)
- Writings on education, undated (Box-folder 15: 11)
- PRD papers, 1990s (Box-folder 16: 1)
- POCM Correspondence, 1940s (Box-folder 16: 2)
- PCM and PSUM documents, 1981 (Box-folder 16: 3)
- PCM and POCM Correspondence, 1940-1950 (Box-folder 16: 4)
- Writings on guerilla warfare, undated (Box-folder 16: 5)
- 2000s election (Box-folder 16: 6)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 16: 7)
- Writings on MLN, undated (Box-folder 16: 8)
- Documents on PRD, 2000s (Box-folder 16: 9)
- Aroche Parra candidacy in PRD, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 16: 10)
- Personal correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 16: 11)
- Documents on MAUS, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 16: 12)
- Documents on presidential succession, 1981 (Box-folder 16: 13)
- Articles in Excelsior on EZLN, Cuba, and USA, 1985-1990s (Box-folder 17: 1)
- Writings on Acapulco and land expropriations, undated (Box-folder 17: 2)
- World Conferences on Peace, 1970s (Box-folder 17: 3)
- PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 17: 4)
- Notes and correspondence on MAUS, PCM, and POCM and issue of amnesty, undated (Box-folder 17: 5)
- Notes and correspondence on MAUS, PCM, and POCM, undated (Box-folder 17: 6)
- PEMEX correspondence, undated (Box-folder 17: 7)
- Information on Ruben Figueroa, Governor of Acapulco, and police violence, undated (Box-folder 17: 8)
- Copies of articles in Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 17: 9)
- PCM documents, 1940s (Box-folder 17: 10)
- Newspaper writings and clippings, 1940-1990 (Box-folder 18: 1)
- Copies of articles from Excelsior, undated (Box-folder 18: 2)
- Correspondence and documents of the National Directory of POCM, 1950s (Box-folder 18: 3)
- Correspondence and documents on rail strikes of 1958-1959 and labor organizing in 1950s (Box-folder 18: 4)
- Articles from Excelsior, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 18: 5-6)
- Copies of cultural magazine Cuauhtemoc, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 19: 1)
- Copies of articles published in Excelsior and El Sol de Acapulco, 1990s (Box-folder 19: 2)
- Communiqué to Jorge Madrazo, head of National Commission of Human Rights, on repression of oil workers at PEMEX, 1993 (Box-folder 19: 3)
- Miscellaneous political writings from 1970s to 2000s on topics such as the US invasion of Iraq and the 2000 Mexican presidential election (Box-folder 19: 4)
- Miscellaneous political writings from 1980s on political corruption, fraud, and de la Madrid and Salinas governments (Box-folder 19: 5)
- Miscellaneous political writings from 1990s and PRD ephemera (Box-folder 19: 6)
- Copies of articles and political documents, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 19: 7)
- Documents from POCM, 1950s (Box-folder 19: 8)
- Documents on MAUS from 1970s and PFCRN of 1990s (Box-folder 19: 9)
- Political documents and correspondence of PCM and MAUS, 1970s (Box-folder 19: 10)
- Documents First National Conference of Women Workers, 1956 (Box-folder 19: 11)
- ADN and PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 19: 12-13)
- Copies of Articles, 1940s (Box-folder 20: 1)
- MAUS and PPM documents, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 20: 2)
- MAUS Documents, 1970s (Box-folder 20: 3)
- Articles and correspondence, 1980-2000 (Box-folder 20: 4-5)
- Regional POCM committee documents and newspaper articles, 1950s (Box-folder 20: 6)
- Newspaper clippings on labor struggles, 1950s (Box-folder 20: 7)
- POCM correspondence, 1940-1960 (Box-folder 20: 8)
- News clippings on health, medicine, and fertility, 1980s (Box-folder 20: 9)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 20: 10)
- Documents Parlamento Mundial de los Pueblos por La Paz, 1980 September 23-27 (Box-folder 20: 11)
- ADN documents, 1990s and MAUS documents, 1980s (Box-folder 21: 1)
- PCM and POCM documents, 1950-1980 (Box-folder 21: 2)
- MAUS and PSUM documents, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 21: 3)
- FPN Documents and articles, 1990s (Box-folder 21: 4)
- PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 21: 5)
- Collection of articles on PRD, 1990s (Box-folder 21: 6)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 21: 7)
- Documents on MAUS, 1970s (Box-folder 21: 8)
- Copies of articles, 1990s (Box-folder 22: 1)
- PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 22: 2)
- Documents on MAUS, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 22: 3)
- POCM documents, 1950s (Box-folder 22: 4)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1990s (Box-folder 22: 5)
- PRD documents, 1990 (Box-folder 22: 6)
- Index on “El Che, Genaro y Las Guerrillas,”, undated (Box-folder 22: 7)
- Writings on Sino-Soviet split, undated (Box-folder 22: 8)
- Miscellaneous political documents and ephemera, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 22: 9-11)
- Copies of El Despertador 1970s and other documents, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 22: 12)
- ADN and PRD documents, 2000s (Box-folder 23: 1)
- “La Derrota Ferrocarrilera” written in prison, 1960 September 9 (Box-folder 23: 2)
- 1989 Constitutional Reforms (Box-folder 23: 3)
- Documents and clippings from imprisonment and on Sino-Soviet split, 1960s (Box-folder 23: 4)
- MAUS documents, 1970s (Box-folder 23: 5)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 23: 6)
- Articles and Correspondence, 1960s (Box-folder 23: 7)
- Copies of articles for Excelsior, 1970-2000 (Box-folder 23: 8-9)
- Documents on Frente Patriotico Nacional (FPN), 1990s (Box-folder 24: 1)
- Documents on Asambla Democratica por el Sufragio Efectivo (ADESE) and elections and electoral fraud, 1990s (Box-folder 24: 2)
- Documents on PRD, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 24: 3)
- Forum magazine, 1980s, 2008 (Box-folder 24: 4)
  Includes copies of articles and press clippings.
- 1970s articles on Guerrero, political violence, and human rights (Box-folder 24: 5)
- Copies of La Voz Obrera and other publications; Articles from column “Facetas de Guerrero” and PPS documents, 1970s (Box-folder 24: 6)
- Miscellaneous documents on labor, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 24: 7)
- Letter to José Santos Valdés, 1965 February 23 (Box-folder 24: 8)
- Documents on MAUS, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 24: 9-10)
  Includes documents on university issues.
- Copies of “La Unidad” “El Socialista” and other political party ephemera, 1970s (Box-folder 25: 1)
- PRD and Acuerdo Nacional para la Democracia (ACNDE), 1990s (Box-folder 25: 2)
- Documents on Figuero family of Guerrero, undated (Box-folder 25: 3)
- Correspondence between PCM, POCM and MAUS on imprisonment of ferrocarrileros, 1960s (Box-folder 25: 4)
- Articles on Campeche, 1990s (Box-folder 25: 5)
- Railroad labor, 1977 (Box-folder 25: 6)
- Buro de Investigacion Politica (BIP) documents 1981 and copies of Pueblo (1981), Insurgencia Popular (1981) and El Insurgente Socialista (1978) (Box-folder 25: 7)
- Documents from Camarada de Diputados as PRD representative, 1990s (Box-folder 25: 8)
- Correspondence to Aroche Parra family, 1960s (Box-folder 25: 9)
- 1950s writings on Acapulco (Box-folder 25: 10)
- Documents on Cuauhtémoc Cárdenas, 1990s (Box-folder 25: 11)
- Documents on political and electoral fraud, 1990s (Box-folder 25: 12)
- Copies of column “Facetas de Guerrero,”, undated (Box-folder 25: 13)
- Documents on Vietnam and correspondence on agriculture, 1950s (Box-folder 25: 14)
- Copies of Articles on variety of topics, particularly anti-imperialism, 1970s (Box-folder 25: 15)
- Newspaper articles on Guerrero, 1980s (Box-folder 25: 16)
- Miscellaneous political pamphlets, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 26: 1)
- Copies of Alcance, 1952 (Box-folder 26: 2)
- Correspondence on education issues, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 26: 3)
- Miscellaneous political pamphlets, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 26: 4)
- Materials on elections and political parties, 1970-2000 (Box-folder 26: 5)
- Notes and writings from Guerrero state committee of PCM, 1940s (Box-folder 26: 6)
- Miscellaneous political documents, 1970-2000 (Box-folder 26: 7)
- Copies of Excelsior articles, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 26: 8)
- “El Curso Campesino,”, 1939 (Box-folder 26: 9)
- Correspondence between Parra and MAUS, 1970s (Box-folder 27: 1)
- POCM files, 1954-1976 (Box-folder 27: 2)
- Documents on agriculture, copies of Militante, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 27: 3)
- PRD documents; Copies of Excelsior articles, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 27: 4)
- Miscellaneous articles and political documents, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 27: 5)
- “La Constitution Mexicana de 1917 y Los Derechos Sociales” and various articles and poetry about Lazaro Cárdenas and Mexican politics, undated (Box-folder 27: 6)
- Documents on Sino-Soviet split, 1960s (Box-folder 27: 7)
- Documents on ADESE and political corruption, 1990s (Box-folder 27: 8)
- Copy of 1901 “Coleccion de Documents para la Historica Mexicana” by Dr. Antonio Peñafiel (Box-folder 27: 9)
- PRD documents, undated (Box-folder 27: 10)
- Copy of “Tiempo de Mexico” (1821), Femedes (1984); Documents of ADN and PRD, 2000s (Box-folder 27: 11)
- Correspondence, 1950s (Box-folder 27: 12)
  Includes copies of “La Internacional” 1970s and “Informacion sobre el Plan Global de Desarollo 1980-1982.”
- Copies of articles published in Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 27: 13)
- PCM and POCM documents, 1940-1970 (Box-folder 28: 1)
- Copies of articles in Excelsior, 1990s (Box-folder 28: 2)
- Articles on XIX Congress of PCM (1981); Copy of El Constructor publication of POCM (1954), and PPS and MAUS documents (1970s) (Box-folder 28: 3)
- Various writings, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 28: 4)
- PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 28: 5-6)
- ADESE Documents, 1989 (Box-folder 28: 7)
- Writings on agriculture in Guerrero and Yucatan, 1950s (Box-folder 28: 8)
- Writings and correspondence of POCM and PCM, 1940s (Box-folder 28: 9)
- Copies of articles published in Excelsior, 1980s (Box-folder 28: 10)
- PRD documents and documents on Amnesty Law in Guerrero, 1990s (Box-folder 28: 11)
- Documents of ADN, MAUS 1950s to 1990s, and writings on ferrocarrilero strike of 1958-1959 (Box-folder 28: 12)
- Correspondence in periodicals Liberacion and Punto Critica on behalf of MAUS, POCM and other parties, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 29: 1)
- Copies of articles, 1990s (Box-folder 29: 2)
- PRD documents, 1990s (Box-folder 29: 3)